<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Maiesties speech to both the houses of Parliament, in his Highnesse great chamber at Whitehall, the day of the adiournement of the last session, which was the last day of March 1607</title>
            <title>Speeches. 1607-03-31</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68249</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843324_8048</idno>
  <idno type="VID">8048</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248573894</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 14395</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107626</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99843324e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 672:09, 739:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Maiesties speech to both the houses of Parliament, in his Highnesse great chamber at Whitehall, the day of the adiournement of the last session, which was the last day of March 1607</title>
                  <title>Speeches. 1607-03-31</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1607]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Concerning the proposed union with Scotland.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴ H² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" with part of a headpiece; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: His Maiesties speech at White-hall.</note>
                  <note>Copies vary; B2v line 4 ends "when" or "me"; other differences.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 14395a on UMI microfilm reel 672.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Folger Shakespeare Library and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 672 (Folger Shakespeare Library copy) and at reel 739 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:1"/>
            <p>HIS MAIESTIES SPEECH TO BOTH the Houses of Parliament, in <hi>his Highnesse great Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the day of the Adiournement of the last Session, <hi>Which was the last day of</hi> March 1607.</p>
            <p>¶ IMPRINTED AT London by <hi>Robert Barker,</hi> Printer to the Kings most Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maiestie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing receiued (gentle Reader) diuers and different Copies of his Maiesties Speech to this last Session of Parliament in Whitehall, at their recession in the Passion weeke; my labour hath bene to conferre all these copies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with the helpe of some gentlemen that were auditors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to make such an extraction as J here present vnto thee. Which though J dare not maintaine to bee a true and full relation of all his Maiestie spake, as beeing farre
<pb facs="tcp:8048:3"/>short both of the life of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties eloquent phrases, and fulnesse of the matter: yet seeing (as I hope) it conteines most of the substantiall reasons and Arguments that therein were vttered, and that it is a thing desired by so many, though not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related by any, J haue taken the boldnesse to present it vnto thee, such as it is, being the rather at mine owne suite permitted to Print it, for es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing the wrong that might be done vnto thee, by the publishing of so many false copies that begin already to be spread thereof. And thus hoping of thy kinde acceptance of this my well meant labour, J bid thee farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:3"/>
            <head>HIS MAIESTIES SPEECH TO BOTH the Houses of Parliament, in <hi>his Highnesse great Chamber</hi> at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the day of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iournement of the last Session, which was the last day of March 1607.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lords of the higher House, and you Knights &amp; Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesses of the Lower house, All men at the beginning of a Feast bring foorth good wine first, and after, worse. This was the saying of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Feast at <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galile,</hi> where
<pb facs="tcp:8048:4"/>CHRIST wrought his first miracle by changing water into wine. But in this case now whereof I am to speake vnto you, I must follow that Gouernours rule, and not CHRISTS example, in giuing you the worst and sowrest wine last. For all the time of this long Session of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you haue bin so fed and cloy'd, (spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially you of the Lower house) with such banquets, and choise of delicate speeches, and your eares so seasoned with the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of long precogitate Orations; as this my Speech now in the breaking vp of this Assembly, cannot but appeare vnto your taste as the worst wine proposed in the end of the Banquet, since I am onely to deliuer nowe vnto you matter without curious forme, substance without ceremonie, trueth in all sinceritie. Yet considering the Person that speaketh, the parties to whom I speake, the matter whereof I meane to speake; it fits better to vtter matter, rather then words, in regard of the greatnesse of my place who am to speake to you, the
<pb facs="tcp:8048:4"/>grauitie of you the Auditorie, which is the high Court of Parliament; the weight of the matter, which concernes the securitie and establishment of this whole Empire, and litle world. Studied Orations and much eloquence vpon litle matter is fitte for the Vniuersities, where not the Subiect which is spoken of, but the triall of his wit that speaketh, is most commendable: but on the contrary, in all great Councels of Parliaments fewest words with most mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doeth become best, where the dispatch of the great errandes in hand, and not the prayse of the person is most to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto: like the garment of a chaste wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who is onely set forth by her naturall beautie, which is properly her owne: other deckings are but ensignes of an harlot that flyes with borrowed feathers. And besides the conueniencie, I am forced hereunto by necessitie, my place calling mee to acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not leauing mee to the libertie of contemplation, hauing alwayes my thoughts busied with the publique care of
<pb facs="tcp:8048:5"/>you all, where euery one of you hauing but himselfe and his owne priuate to thinke of, are at more leisure to make studied speeches. And therefore the matter which I deliuer you confusedly as in a sacke, I leaue it to you when you are in your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and haue better leysure then I can haue, to ranke them in order, euery one in their owne place.</p>
            <p>Thus much by way of Preface. But I proceed to the matter. Whereof I might say with <hi>S. Paul,</hi> I could speake in as many tongues as you all, but I had rather speake three wordes to edification, then talke all day without vnderstanding. In vaine (sayth the <hi>Psalmist</hi>) doeth the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der build the house, or the watchman watch the Citie, vnlesse the Lord giue his blessing thereunto. And in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament <hi>S. Paul</hi> saith, That he may plant, <hi>Apollo</hi> may water, but it is GOD onely that must giue the increase. This I speake, because of the long time which hath bene spent about the Treatie of the Vnion.
<pb facs="tcp:8048:5"/>For my selfe, I protest vnto you all, When I first propounded the Vnion, I then thought there could haue bene no more question of it, then of your declaration and acknowledgement of my Right vnto this Crowne, and that, as two Twinnes, they would haue growen vp together. The error was my mistaking; I knew mine owne ende, but not others feares. But now finding many crossings, long dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, strange questions, and nothing done; I must needes thinke it proceeds ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mistaking of the errand, or else from some iealousie of me the Propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that you so adde delay vnto delay, searching out as it were the very bowels of Curiositie, and conclude nothing. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I condemne you for being yet in some iealousie of my intention in this matter, hauing not yet had so great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of my behauiour and inclination in these fewe yeeres past, as you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture haue in a longer time hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and not hauing occasion to consult
<pb facs="tcp:8048:6"/>daily with my selfe, and heare mine owne opinion in all those particulars which are debated among you. But heere I pray you now mistake me not at the first, when as I seeme to finde fault with your delayes and curiositie, as if I would haue you to resolue in an houres time, that which will take a moneths aduisement: for you all knowe, that <hi>Rex est Lex loquens,</hi> and you haue oft heard me say, That the Kings will and intention being the speaking Law, ought to be <hi>Luce clarius:</hi> and I hope you of the Lower house haue the proofe of this my cleerenesse by a Bill sent you down from the Vpper house within these fewe dayes, or rather few houres: wherein may very well appeare vnto you the care I haue to put my Subiects in a good secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of their possessions for all posterities to come. And therefore that you may cleerely vnderstand my meaning in that point, I doe freely confesse, you had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to aduise at leasure vpon so great a cause: for great matters doe euer require
<pb facs="tcp:8048:6"/>great deliberation before they bee well concluded. <hi>Deliberandum est diu quod sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuendum est semel.</hi> Consultations must pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>lento pede,</hi> but the execution of a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vpon the resolution would be spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. If you will goe on, it matters not though you goe with leaden feete, so you make still some progresse, and that there be no let or needlesse delay, and doe not <hi>Nodum in scirpo quaerere.</hi> I am euer for the <hi>Medium</hi> in euery thing. Betweene foolish rashnesse and extreame length, there is a middle way. Search all that is reasonable, but omit that which is idle, curious and vnnecessarie; otherwise, there can neuer be a resolution or end in any good worke.</p>
            <p>And now from the generall I will des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to particulars, and will onely for the ease of your memories diuide the matter that I am to speake of, into foure heads, by opening vnto you, First, what I craue: Secondly, in what manner I desire it: Thirdly, what commodities will ensue to both the Kingdoms by it: Fourthly, what
<pb facs="tcp:8048:7"/>the supposed inconueniencie may be that giues impediments thereunto.</p>
            <p>For the first, what I craue, I protest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God who knowes my heart, and to you my People before whome it were a shame to lie, that I claime nothing but with acknowledgement of my Bond to you; that as yee owe to me subiection and obedience: So my Soueraigntie obligeth me to yeeld to your loue Gouernment and protection: Neither did I euer wish any happinesse to my selfe, which was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned with the happinesse of my people. I desire a perfect Vnion of Lawes and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and such a Naturalizing as may make one body of both Kingdomes vnder mee your King, That I and my Posteritie (if it so please God) may rule ouer you to the worlds end; Such an Vnion as was of the Scots and Pickes in Scotland, and of the Heptarchie heere in England. And for Scotland I auow such an Vnion as if you had got it by Conquest, but such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest as may be cemented by loue, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:8048:7"/>sure bond of subiection or friendship: that as there is ouer both but <hi>vnus Rex,</hi> so there may bee in both but <hi>vnus Grex &amp; vna Lex:</hi> For no more possible is it for one King to gouerne two Countreys <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiguous,</hi> the one a great, the other a lesse, a richer and a poorer, the greater drawing like an Adamant the lesser to the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities therof, then for one head to gouerne two bodies, or one man to bee husband of two wiues, whereof Christ himselfe said, <hi>Ab initio non fuit sic.</hi> But in the generall Vnion you must obserue two things: for I will discouer my thoughts plainely vnto you; I studie clearenesse, not eloquence, And therefore with the old Philosophers, I would heartily wish my breast were a transparent Glasse for you all to see through, that you might looke into my heart, and then would you bee satisfied of my meaning. For when I speake of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Vnion, I meane not confusion of all things: you must not take from Scotland those particular Priuiledges that may stand
<pb facs="tcp:8048:8"/>as well with this Vnion, as in England ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular customes in particular Shires, (as the Customes of Kent, and the Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Countie Palatine of Chester) doe with the Common Law of the Kingdome: for euery particular shire almost, and much more euery Countie, haue some particular Customes that are as it were naturally most fit for that people. But I meane of such a generall Vnion of Lawes as may reduce the whole Iland, that as they liue already vnder one Monarch, so they may all bee gouerned by one Law. For I must needes confesse by that little experience I haue had since my comming hither, and I thinke I am able to prooue it, that the grounds of the Common Lawe of England, are the best of any Law in the world, either Ciuill or Municipall, and the fittest for this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But as euery Law would be cleere and full, so the obscuritie in some points of this our written Lawe, and want of fulnesse in others, the variation of Cases and mens curiositie breeding euery day new questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:8048:8"/>hath enforced the Iudges to iudge in many Cases here, by Cases and presidents, wherein I hope Lawyers themselues will not denie but that there must be a great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie, and I am sure all the rest of you that are Gentlemen of other professions were long agoe wearie of it, if you could haue had it amended. For where there is varietie and vncertaintie, although a iust Iudge may doe rightly, yet an ill Iudge may take aduantage to doe wrong: and then are all honest men that succeede him, tied in a maner to his vniust and partiall conclusions. Wherefore, leaue not the Lawe to the pleasure of the Iudge, but let your Lawes bee looked into: for I desire not the abolishing of the Lawes, but onely the clearing and the sweeping of the rust of them, and that by Parliament our Lawes might bee cleared and made knowen to all the Subiects. Yea rather it were lesse hurt, that all the approued Cases were set down and allowed by Parliament for standing Lawes in all time to come. For although
<pb facs="tcp:8048:9"/>some of them peraduenture may be vniust as set downe by corrupt Iudges; yet better it is to haue a certaine Lawe with some spots in it, nor liue vnder such an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and arbitrarie Law, since as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe is, It is lesse harme to suffer an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience then a mischiefe. And now may you haue faire occasion of amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and polishing your Lawes, when Scotland is to bee vnited with you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them: for who can blame Scotland to say, If you will take away our owne Lawes, I pray you giue vs a better and cleerer in place thereof. But this is not possible to be done without a fit prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hee that buildeth a Ship, must first prouide the timber; and as Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe said, No man will build an house, but hee will first prouide the materials: nor a wise king will not make warre against ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without hee first make prouision of money: and all great workes must haue their preparation: and that was my end in causing the Instrument of the Vnion to
<pb facs="tcp:8048:9"/>be made. Vnion is a mariage: would hee not be thought absurd that for furthering of a mariage betweene two friends of his, would make his first motion to haue the two parties be laid in bedde together, and performe the other turnes of mariage? must there not precede the mutuall sight and acquaintance of the parties one with another, the conditions of the contract, and Ioincture to be talked of and agreed vpon by their friends, and such other things as in order ought to goe before the ending of such a worke? The vnion is an eternall agreement and reconciliation of many long bloody warres that haue bene betweene these two ancient Kingdomes. Is it the readiest way to agree a priuate quarell betweene two, to bring them at the first to shake hands, and as it were kisse other, and lie vnder one roofe or rather in one bedde together, before that first the ground of their quarell be communed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their mindes mitigated, their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons prepared, and all other circumstances
<pb facs="tcp:8048:10"/>first vsed, that ought to be vsed to proceed to such a finall agreement? Euery honest man desireth a perfect Vnion, but they that say so, and admit no preparation thereto, haue <hi>mel in ore, fel in corde.</hi> If af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your so long talke of Vnion in all this long Session of Parliament, yee rise with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out agreeing vpon any particular; what will the neighbour Princes iudge, whose eyes are all fixed vpon the conclusion of this Action, but that the King is refused in his desire, whereby the Nation should be taxed, and the King disgraced? And what an ill preparation is it for the mindes of Scotland toward the Vnion, when they shall heare that ill is spoken of their whole Nation, but nothing is done nor aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the matter of the Vnion it selfe? But this I am glad was but the fault of one, and one is no number: yet haue your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of Scotland this aduantage of you, that none of them hath spoken ill of you (nor shall as long as I am King) in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any such publique place of Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature.
<pb facs="tcp:8048:10"/>Consider therefore well, if the mindes of Scotland had not neede to be well prepared to perswade their mutuall consent, seeing you here haue all the great aduantage by the Vnion. Is not here the personall residence of the King, his whole Court and family? Is not here the seate of Iustice, and the fountaine of Gouernment? must they not be subiected to the Lawes of England, and so with time become but as Cumberland and Northumberland, and those other remote and Northerne Shires? you are to be the husband, they the wife: you conquerours, they as conquered, though not by the sword, but by the sweet and sure bond of loue. Besides that, they as other Northerne Countreys will be sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome seene and saluted by their King, and that as it were but in a posting or hunting iourney.</p>
            <p>How little cause then they may haue of such a change of so ancient a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie into the case of priuate Shires, iudge rightly herein. And that you may bee the
<pb facs="tcp:8048:11"/>more vpright Iudges, suppose your selues the Patients of whom such sentence should bee giuen. But what preparation is it which I craue? onely such as by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance may shew something is done, yet more is intended. There is a conceipt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, and a double iealousie possesseth many, wherein I am misiudged.</p>
            <p>First, that this Vnion wil be the <hi>Crisis</hi> to the ouerthrow of England, and setting vp of Scotland: England will then bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed by the swarming of the Scots, who if the Vnion were effected, would raigne and rule all.</p>
            <p>The second is, my profuse liberalitie to the Scottish men more then the English, and that with this Vnion all things shalbe giuen to them, and you turned out of all: To you shall be left the sweat and labour, to them shall bee giuen the fruite and sweet; and that my forbearance is but till this Vnion may bee gained. How agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able this is to the trueth, Iudge you; And that not by my wordes, but by my Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb facs="tcp:8048:11"/>Doe I craue the Vnion without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions? doe I not offer to binde my selfe and to reserue to you, as in the Instrument, all places of Iudicature? doe I intend any thing which standeth not with the equall good of both Nations? I could then haue done it, and not spoken of it: For all men of vnderstanding must agree, that I might dispose without assent of Parliament, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Iudicature, and others, both Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall and Temporall. But herein I did voluntarily offer by my Letters from Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston to the Commissioners, to binde my Prerogatiue.</p>
            <p>Some thinke that I will draw the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Nation hither, talking idlely of trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of Trees out of a barren ground into a better, and of leane cattell out of bad pasture into a more fertile soile. Can any man displant you, vnlesse you will? or can any man thinke that Scotland is so strong to pull you out of your houses? or doe you not thinke I know England hath more people, Scotland more wast
<pb facs="tcp:8048:12"/>ground? So that there is roumth in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land rather to plant your idle people that swarme in London streets, and other Townes, and disburthen you of them, then to bring more vnto you; And in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Iustice, if I be partiall to either side, let my owne mouth condemne me, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be your King.</p>
            <p>I appeale to your selues, if in fauour or Iustice I haue bene partiall. Nay, my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was euer, you should then haue most cause to praise my discretion, when you saw I had most power. If hitherto I haue done nothing to your preiudice, much lesse meane I hereafter. If when I might haue done it without any breach of promise; Thinke so of me, that much lesse I will doe it, when a Law is to restraine me. I owe no more to the Scottish men then to the English. I was borne there, and sworne here, and now raigne ouer both. Such particular persons of the Scottish Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as might claime any extraordinary merit at my handes, I haue already rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably
<pb facs="tcp:8048:12"/>rewarded, and I can assure you that there is none left, whom for I meane extraordinary to straine my selfe further, then in such ordinary benefit as I may equally bestow without mine owne great hurt, vpon any Subiect of either Nation; In which case no Kings handes can euer be fully closed. To both I owe Iustice and protection, which with Gods grace I shall euer equally ballance.</p>
            <p>For my Liberalitie, I haue told you of it heretofore: my three first yeeres were to me as a Christmas, I could not then bee miserable: should I haue bene ouersparing to them? they might haue thought <hi>Ioseph</hi> had forgotten his brethren, or that the King had bene drunke with his new King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But Suites goe not so cheape as they were wont, neither are there so many sees taken in the Hamper and Pettibagge for the great Seale as hath bene. And if I did respect the English when I came first, of whom I was receiued with ioy, and came as in a hunting iourney, what might the
<pb facs="tcp:8048:13"/>Scottish haue iustly said, if I had not in some measure dealt bountifully with them that so long had serued me, so farre aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured themselues with me, and beene so faithfull to mee. I haue giuen you now foure yeeres proofe since my comming, and what I might haue done more to haue raised the Scottish nation you all know, and the longer I liue, the lesse cause haue I to be acquainted with them, and so the lesse hope of extraordinary fauour towards them: For since my comming from them I doe not alreadie know the one halfe of them by face, most of the youth being now risen vp to be men, who were but children when I was there, and more are borne since my comming thence.</p>
            <p>Now for my lands and reuenues of my Crowne which you may thinke I haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minished, they are not yet so farre dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, but that I thinke no prince of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome hath fairer possessions to his Crowne then yet I haue, and in token of my care to preserue the same to my posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:8048:13"/>for euer, the intaile of my lands to the Crowne hath bene long agoe offered vnto you: and that it is not yet done, is not my fault as you know. My Treasurer here knoweth my care, and hath already in part declared it, and if I did not hope to treble my Reuenue more then I haue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired it, I should neuer rest quietly in my bed. But notwithstanding my comming to the Crowne, with that extraordinarie applause which you all know, and that. I had two Nations to be the obiects of my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie, which neuer any Prince had here before; will you compare my gifts out of mine inheritance with some Princes here that had onely this Nation to respect, and whose whole time of reigne was litle lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then mine hath bene already? It will be found that their gifts haue farre surpas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed mine, albeit as I haue already said, they had nothing so great cause of vsing their liberalitie.</p>
            <p>For the maner of the Vnion presently desired, It standeth in 3. parts: The first,
<note place="margin">Secondly</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8048:14"/>taking away of hostile Lawes: for since there can be now no Warres betwixt you, is it not reason hostile Lawes should cease? For, <hi>deficiente causa deficit effectus.</hi> The King of England now cannot haue warres with the King of Scotland, therefore this failes of it selfe. The second is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Commerce. I am no stranger vnto you: for you all knowe I came from the loines of your ancient Kings. They of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land be my Subiects as you are. But how can I bee naturall Liege Lord to you both, and you strangers one to the other? Shall they which be of one alleagance with you, be no better respected of you, nor freer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you, then Frenchmen and Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, since I am Soueraigne ouer both? You as Subiects to one King, it must needes follow that you conuerse and haue Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce together. There is a rumour of some ill dealings that should bee vsed by the Commissioners, Merchants of Scotland. They be heere in England, and shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine till your next meeting, and abide
<pb facs="tcp:8048:14"/>triall, to prooue themselues either honest men or knaues.</p>
            <p>For the third point, of Naturalization,
<note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> All you agree that they are no Aliens, and yet will not allow them to bee naturall. What kind of prerogatiue vvill you make? But for the <hi>Post nati,</hi> your owne Lawyers and Iudges at my first comming to this Crowne, informed me, there was a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the <hi>Antè</hi> and the <hi>Post nati</hi> of each Kingdomes, which caused me to publish a Proclamation, that the <hi>Post nati</hi> were Naturalized <hi>(Ipso facto)</hi> by my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession to this Crowne. I doe not denie but Iudges may erre as men, and therefore I doe not presse you here to sweare to all their reasons. I onely vrge at this time the conueniencie for both Kingdomes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pressing you to iudge nor to bee iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. But remember also it is as possible and likely your owne Lawyers may erre as the Iudges. Therefore as I wish you to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede herein so farre as may tend to the weale of both Nations: So would I haue
<pb facs="tcp:8048:15"/>you oh the other part to beware to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace either my Proclamations or the Iudges, who when the Parliament is done, haue power to trie your lands and liues, for so you may disgrace both your King and your Lawes. For the doing of any act that may procure lesse reuerence to the Iudges, cannot but breede a loosenesse in the Gouernment, and a disgrace to the whole Nation. The reason that most mooues mee for ought I haue yet heard, that there cannot but bee a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Antè nati</hi> and the <hi>Post nati,</hi> and that in the fauour of the last, is that they must bee neerer vnto you being borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the present Gouernment and common Alleageance: but in point of conueniencie, there is no question but the <hi>Post nati</hi> are more to bee respected, For if you would haue a perfect and perpetuall Vnion, that cannot bee in the <hi>Antè nati,</hi> who are but few in comparison of those that shall be in all Ages succeeding and cannot liue long. But in the <hi>Post nati</hi> shall the Vnion be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb facs="tcp:8048:15"/>and liue euer age after age, which wanting a difference cannot but leaue a perpetual marke of separation in the worke of the Vnion: as also that argument of iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie will be so farre remooued in the case of the <hi>Post nati</hi> which are to reape the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit in all succeeding Ages, as by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie there will then rise <hi>Pharaos</hi> which neuer knew <hi>Ioseph.</hi> The Kings my Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours, who being borne and bred here, can neuer haue more occasion of acquaintance with the Scottish nation in generall, then any other English King that was before my time. Be not therefore abafed with the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering speeches of such as would haue the <hi>Antè nati</hi> preferred, alleadging their merit in my Seruice, and such other reasons which indeed are but Sophismes. For, my rēwarding out of my Liberalitie of any particular men, hath nothing adoe with the generall acte of the Vnion, which must not regard the deserts of priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, but the generall weale and conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Nations. Besides that, the
<pb facs="tcp:8048:16"/>actuall Naturalizing, which is the onely point that is in your handes, is already granted to by your selues to the most part of such particular persons as can haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vse of it heere: and if any other well deseruing men were to sue for it hereafter, I doubt not but there would neuer be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion mooued among you for the granting of it. And therefore it is most euident, that such discoursers haue <hi>mel in ore, fel in corde,</hi> as I said before; carying an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance of loue to the Vnion, but indeed a contrary resolution in their hearts. And as for limitations and respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, such as shall by me be agreed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be reasonable and necessarie after you haue fully debated vpon them, you may assure your selues I will with indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie grant what is requisite without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall respect of Scotland I am, as I haue often said, borne and sworne king ouer both Kingdomes; onely this farre let me entreat you, in debating the point at your next meeting, That ye be as ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue
<pb facs="tcp:8048:16"/>doubts as to mooue them, and to be satisfied when doubts are cleered.</p>
            <p>And as for Commodities that come by he Vnion of these Kingdomes,
<note place="margin">Third.</note> they are great and euident; Peace, Plentie, Loue, free Intercourse and common Societie of two great Nations. All foreigne Kings that haue sent their Ambassadours to congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate with me since my comming, haue saluted me as Monarch of the whole Isle, and with much more respect of my great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, then if I were King alone of one of these Realmes: and with what comfort doe your selues behold Irish, Scottish, Welsh, and English, diuers in Nation, yet all walking as Subiects and seruants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my Court, and all liuing vnder the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance of your King, besides the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and lustre that the encrease of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant men in the Court of diuers Nations caries in the eyes of all strangers that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire hither? Those confining places which were the Borders of the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, where heretofore much blood was
<pb facs="tcp:8048:17"/>shed, and many of your ancestours lost their liues; yea, that lay waste and deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and were habitations but for runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, are now become the Nauell or Vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilicke of both Kingdomes, planted and peopled with ciuilitie and riches: their Churches begin to be planted, their doores stand now open, they feare neither rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing nor spoiling: and where there was nothing before heard nor seene in those parts but bloodshed, oppressions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and outcries, they now liue euery man peaceably vnder his owne figgetree, and all their former cryes and complaints turned onely into prayers to God for their King, vnder whome they enioy such ease and happie quietnesse. The Marches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond and on this side Twede, are as fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and as peaceable as most parts of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland: If after all this there shall be a Scis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, what inconuenience will follow, iudge you.</p>
            <p>And as for the inconueniences that are feared on Englands part, It is alleadged,
<pb facs="tcp:8048:17"/>that the Scots are a populous Nation, they shall be harboured in our nests, they shall be planted and flourish in our good Soile, they shall eate our commons bare, and make vs leane: These are foolish and idle surmises. That which you possesse, they are not to enioy; by Law they cannot, nor by my partialitie they shall not: for set apart conscience and honour, (which if I should set apart indeed, I had rather wish my selfe to be set apart and out of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) can any man conclude either out of common reason or good policie, that I will preferre those which perhaps I shall neuer see, or but by poste for a moneth, before those with whome I must alwayes dwell? Can they conquer or ouercome you with swarmes of people, as the Goths and the Vandals did <hi>Italy?</hi> Surely the world knowes they are nothing so populous as you are: and although they haue had the honour and good fortune neuer to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, yet were they euer but vpon the defensiue part, and may in a part thanke
<pb facs="tcp:8048:18"/>their hilles and inaccessible passages that preserued them from an vtter ouerthrow at the hands of all that pretended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer them. Or are they so very poore and miserable in their owne habitations, that necessitie should force them all to make incursions among you?</p>
            <p>And for my part, when I haue two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnder my gouernment, can you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine I wil respect the lesser, and neglect the greater? would I not thinke it a lesse euill and hazard to me that the plague were at Northampton or Barwicke, then at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, so neere Westminster, the Seat of my habitation, and of my wife and children? will not a man be more carefull to quench the fire taken in his neerest neighbours house, then if a whole Towne were a fire farre from him? You know that I am care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to preserue the woods &amp; game through all England, nay, through all the Isle: yet none of you doubts, but that I would bee more offended with any disorder in the Forrest of Waltham, for stealing of a
<pb facs="tcp:8048:18"/>Stagge there, which lieth as it were vnder my nose, and in a maner ioyneth with my garden, then with cutting of timber, or stealing of a Deare in any Forrest of the North parts of Yorkeshire or the Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke. Thinke you that I will preferre them that be absent, lesse powerfull, and farther off to doe me good or hurt, before you, with whome my securitie and liuing must be, and where I desire to plant my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie? If I might by any such fauours raise my selfe to a greatnesse, it might bee probable: All I cannot draw, and to lose a whole state here to please a few there, were madnesse. I need speake no more of this with protestations. Speake but of a wit, it is not likely: and to doubt of my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this, were more then deuilish.</p>
            <p>For mine owne part, I offer more then I receiue, and conueniencie I preferre before law, in this poynt. For, three parts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I might hurt this Nation, by partialitie to the Scots, you know do absolutely lie in my hands and power: for either in disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:8048:19"/>of rents, or whatsoeuer benefit, or in the preferring of them to any dignitie or office, ciuill or Ecclesiasticall, or in calling them to the Parliament, it doeth all fully and onely lie within the compasse of my Prerogatiue, which are the parts wherein the Scottish men can receiue either bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite or preferrement by the Vnion, and wherein for the care I haue of this people, I am content to binde my selfe with some reasonable restrictions.</p>
            <p>As for the fourth part, the naturalizing, which onely lieth in your hands; It is the poynt wherein they receiue least benefit of any: for in that they can obteine nothing, but what they buy by their purse, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire by the selfe same meanes that you do. And as for the point of naturalizing, which is the poynt thought so fit, and so precisely belonging to Parliament: not to speake of the Common lawe, wherein as yet I can professe no great knowledge, but in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill law wherein I am a litle better versed, and which in the point of Coniunction of
<pb facs="tcp:8048:19"/>Nations should beare a great sway, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law of Nations: I will mainteine two principles in it, which no learned and graue Ciuilian wil deny, as being clearly to be proued, both out of the text it selfe in many places, and also out of the best ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued Doctours and interpreters of that law, The one, that it is a speciall poynt of the Kings owne Prerogatiue, to make Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens Citizens, and <hi>donare Ciuitate,</hi> The other, that in any case wherein the Law is thought not to be cleared (as some of your selues do doubt, that in this case of the <hi>post nati,</hi> the Law of England doth not clearely determine) then in such a question where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no positiue Law is resolute, <hi>Rex est Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex,</hi> for he is <hi>Lex loquens,</hi> and is to supply the law, where the law wants, and if ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny famous histories be to be beleeued, they giue the example for mainteining of this law in the persons of the Kings of England and France especially, whose speciall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue they alleadge it to be. But this I speake onely as knowing what belongeth
<pb facs="tcp:8048:20"/>to a King, although in this case I presse no further then that which may agree with your loues, and stand with the weale and conueniencie of both Nations.</p>
            <p>And whereas some may thinke this V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion will bring preiudice to some Townes and Corporations within England: It may be, a Merchant or two of Bristow, or Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, may haue an hundred pounds lesse in his packe. But if the Empire gaine, and become the greater, it is no matter: You see one Corporation is euer against another, and no priuate Companie can be set vp, but with some losse to another.</p>
            <p>For the supposed inconueniences rising from Scotland,
<note place="margin">Fourth.</note> they are three. First, that there is an euill affection in the Scottish Nation to the Vnion. Next, the Vnion is incompatible betweene two such Nations. Thirdly, that the gaine is small or none. If this be so, to what end doe we talke of an Vnion? For proofe of the first point, there is alledged an auersenesse in the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Nation expressed in the Instrument,
<pb facs="tcp:8048:20"/>both in the preface and body of their Act; In the preface, where they declare, That they will remaine an absolute and free Monarchie; And in the body of the Acte, where they make an exception of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fundamentall Lawes of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And first for the generall of their auersenesse, All the maine current in your Lower-house ranne this whole Session of Parliament with that opinion, That Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was so greedy of this Vnion, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended that they should receiue so much benefit by it, as they cared not for the strictnesse of any conditions, so they might attaine to the substance: And yet you now say, they are backwards and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse from the Vnion. This is a direct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction <hi>in adiecto:</hi> For, how can they both bee beggers and backwards, in one and the selfe same thing, at the same time?</p>
            <p>But for answere to the particulars, It is an old Schoole point, <hi>Eius est explicare, cuius est condere.</hi> You cannot interpret their Lawes, nor they yours; I that made
<pb facs="tcp:8048:21"/>them with their assent, can best expound them.</p>
            <p>And first I confesse, that the English Parliaments are so long, and the Scottish so short, that a meane betweene them would do well: For the shortnesse of their continuing together, was the cause of their hastie mistaking, by setting these wordes of exception of fundamentall Lawes in the body of the Acte, which they onely did in pressing to imitate word by word the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Instrument, wherein the same words be conteined in your Preface. And as to their meaning and interpretation of that word, I will not onely deliuer it vnto you out of mine owne conceipt, but as it was deliuered vnto mee by the best Lawyers of Scotland, both Counsellours and other Lawyers, who were at the making thereof in Scotland, and were Commissioners here for performance of the same.</p>
            <p>Their meaning in the word of Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes, you shall perceiue more fully hereafter, when I handle the obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:8048:21"/>of the difference of Lawes: For they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thereby onely those Lawes whereby confusion is auoyded, and their Kings des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent mainteined, and the heritage of the succession and Monarchie, which hath bene a kingdome, to which I am in descent, 300. yeeres before CHRIST: Not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, as you doe, of their Common Law, for they haue none, but that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Ius Regis:</hi> and their desire of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a free Monarchie, was onely meant, That al such particular Priuiledges (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I spake before) should not bee so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, as for want either of Magistrate, Law, or order, they might fall in such a confusion, as to become like a naked Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, without Law or libertie vnder this kingdome. I hope you meane not I should set Garrisons ouer them, as the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards doe ouer Sicily and Naples, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne them by Commissioners, which are seldome found succeedingly all wise and honest men.</p>
            <p>This I must say for Scotland, and I may
<pb facs="tcp:8048:22"/>truely vaunt it; Here I sit and gouerne it with my Pen, I write and it is done, and by a Clearke of the Councell I gouerne Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land now, which others could not doe by the sword. And for their auersenesse in their heart against the Vnion, It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, I protest they did neuer craue this Vnion of mee, nor sought it either in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, or the State by letters, nor euer once did any of that Nation presse me forward or wish me to accelerate that businesse. But on the other part, they offered alwayes to obey mee when it should come to them, and all honest men that desire my great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse haue beene thus minded, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall reuerence and regard they beare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Person, and any of my reasonable and iust desires.</p>
            <p>I know there are many <hi>Piggots</hi> amongst them, I meane a number of seditious and discontented particular persons, as must be in all Common-wealths, that where they dare, may peraduenture talke lewdly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: but no Scottish man euer spake dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourably
<pb facs="tcp:8048:22"/>of England in Parliament. For here must I note vnto you the difference of the two Parliaments in these two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; for there they must not speake without the Chauncellors leaue, and if any man doe propound or vtter any seditious or vncomely speeches, he is straight inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and silenced by the Chauncellors authoritie: where as here, the libertie for any man to speake what hee list, and as long as he list, was the onely cause hee was not interrupted. It hath beene obiected, that there is a great Antipathy of the Lawes and Customes of these two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It is much mistaken: for Scotland hath no Common Lawe as here, but the Law they haue is of three sorts.</p>
            <p>All the Lawe of Scotland for Tenures, Wards and Liueries, Seigniories &amp; Lands, are drawen out of the Chauncerie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and for matters of equitie and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things else, differs from you but in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine termes. <hi>Iames</hi> the first, bred here in England, brought the Lawes thither in a
<pb facs="tcp:8048:23"/>written hand. The second is Statute lawes, which be their Acts of Parliament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they haue power as you, to make and alter Lawes: and those may be looked into by you, for I hope you shall bee no more strangers to that Nation. And the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall worke of this Vnion will be, to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the Statute Lawes of both Kingdomes. The third is the Ciuill Law. <hi>Iames</hi> the fift brought it out of France by establishing the Session there, according to the forme of the Court of Parliament of Fraunce, which he had seene in the time of his being there: who occupie there the place of Ciuil Iudges in all matters of Plee or controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, yet not to gouerne absolutely by the Ciuill Law as in France. For if a man plead that the Law of the Nation is otherwise, it is a barre to the Ciuill, and a good Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor or President, will oftentimes repell and put to silence an Argument that the Lawyers brings out of the Ciuill Lawe, where they haue a cleare solution in their owne Lawe. So as the Ciuill Law in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb facs="tcp:8048:23"/>is admitted in no other cases, but to supply such cases wherein the Municipall Law is defectiue. Then may you see it is not so hard a matter as is thought, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce that Countrey to bee vnited with you vnder this Law, which neither are subiect to the Ciuill Lawe, nor yet haue any olde Common Law of their owne, but such as in effect is borrowed from yours. And for their Statute Lawes in Parliament, you may alter and change them as oft as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion shall require, as you doe here. It hath likewise beene obiected as an other impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment, that in the Parliament of Scotland the King hath not a negatiue voice, but must passe all the Lawes agreed on by the Lords and Commons. Of this I can best resolue you: for I am the eldest Parliament man in Scotland, and haue sit in more Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments then any of my Predecessors. I can assure you, that the forme of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there, is nothing inclined to popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. About a twentie dayes or such a time before the Parliament, Proclamation is
<pb facs="tcp:8048:24"/>made throughout the Kingdome, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in to the Kings Clearke of Register (whome you heere call the Master of the Rolles) all Bils to bee exhibited that Session before a certaine day. Then are they brought vnto the King, and perused and considered by him, and onely such as I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of are put into the Chancellors hands to bee propounded to the Parliament, and none others; And if any man in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment speake of any other matter then is in this forme first allowed by me, The Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor tells him there is no such Bill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the King.</p>
            <p>Besides, when they haue passed them for Lawes, they are presented vnto mee, and I with my Scepter put into my hand by the Chancellor, must say, <hi>I ratifie and approoue all things done in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parliament.</hi> And if there bee any thing that I dislike, they rase it out before. If this may bee called a negatiue voyce, then I haue one I am sure in that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:24"/>
            <p> The last impediment is the French li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: which is thought so great, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Scots forsake Fraunce, England cannot bee vnited to them. If the Scottish Nation would bee so vnwilling to leaue them as is said, it would not lye in their hands. For the League was neuer made betweene the people, as is mistaken, but betwixt the PRINCES onely and their Crownes. The beginning was by a Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage from a King of Fraunce, <hi>Charlemaine</hi> I take it (but I cannot certainely remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) vnto a King of Scotland, for a League defensiue and offensiue betweene vs and them against England, Fraunce being at that time in Warres with Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>The like at that time was then desired by England against Fraunce, who also sent their Ambassadours to Scotland. At the first, the Disputation was long main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in fauour of England, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our neerest Neighbours ioyned in one continent, and a strong and powerfull Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:8048:25"/>it was more fitte for the weale and securitie of the State of Scotland, to bee in League and Amitie with them, then with a Countrey, though neuer so strong, yet diuided by Sea from vs: especially England lying betwixt vs and them, where we might bee sure of a suddaine mischiefe, but behooued to abide the hazard of wind and weather, and other accidents that might hinder our reliefe.</p>
            <p>But after, when the contrarie part of the Argument was maintained: wherein allegation was made, that England euer sought to conquer Scotland, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in regarde of their pretended inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in the Kingdome, would neuer keepe any found Amitie with them longer, then they saw their aduantage; whereas France lying more remote and clayming no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in the Kingdome, would therefore bee found a more constant and faithfull friend: It was vnhappily concluded in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the last partie; through which occasion Scotland gate many mischiefes
<pb facs="tcp:8048:25"/>after. And it is by the very tenour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ordered, to be renewed and confirmed from King to King successiuely, which accordingly was euer performed by the mediation of their Ambassadours, and therefore meerely personall, and so was it renewed in the QVEENE my mothers time, onely betweene the two Kings, and not by assent of Parliament or conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the three Estates, which it could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue wanted if it had beene a League betweene the people. And in my time when it came to bee ratified, because it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to bee in <hi>odium tertij,</hi> it was by me left vnrenewed or confirmed as a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible to my Person, in considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Title to this Crowne. Some Priuiledges indeede in the Merchants fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour for point of Commerce, were renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confirmed in my time: wherein for my part of it, there was scarce three Counsellours more then my Secretarie, to whose place it belonged, that medled in that matter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:26"/>
            <p> It is true; that it behooued to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terined, as they call it, in the Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris:</hi> but that onely serues for publication, and not to giue it Author<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: That Parliament (as you know) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a Iudiciall Seate of Iudges and Lawyers, and nothing agreeing with the definition or office of our Parliaments in this Isle. And therefore that any fruites or Priuiledges possessed by the League with Fraunce is able now to remaine in Scotland, is impossible. For yee may be sure, that the French King stayes onely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the sight of the ending of this Vnion, to cut it off himselfe. Otherwise when this great worke were at an end, I would be forced for the generall care I owe to all my Subiects, to craue of France like Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges to them all as Scotland alreadie enioyes, seeing the personall friendship remaines as great betweene vs as between our Progenitors; and all my Subiects must be alike deare vnto mee: which either he will neuer grant, and so all will fall to the
<pb facs="tcp:8048:26"/>ground; or else it will turne to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the whole Island: and so the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Priuiledges cannot hold longer then my League with France lasteth.</p>
            <p>And for another Argument to prooue that this league is only betwene the Kings, and not between the people: They which haue Pensions, or are priuie Intelligence giuers in France without my leaue, are in no better case by the Law of Scotland, then if they were Pensioners to Spaine.</p>
            <p>As for the Scottish Guard in France, the beginning thereof was, when an Eaile of <hi>Boghan</hi> was sent in aide of the French with tenne thousand men, and there being made Constable, and hauing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a victorie, was murthered with the most of the Scottish Armie. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compense whereof, and for a future secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to the Scottish Nation, the Scottish Guard was ordeined to haue the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and prerogatiue before all other Guards in guarding the Kings person.</p>
            <p>And as for the last point of this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuision
<pb facs="tcp:8048:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8048:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8048:28"/>concerning the gaine that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland may make by this Vnion, I thinke no wise nor honest man will aske any such question. For who is so ignorant, that doeth not know the gaine will bee great? Doe you not gaine by the Vnion of Wales? And is not Scotland greater then Wales? Shall not your Dominions bee encreased of Landes, Seas, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons added to your greatnesse? And are not your Landes and Seas adioyning? For who can set downe the limits of the Borders, but as a Mathematicall line or <hi>Idaea?</hi> Then will that backe doore bee shut, and those portes of <hi>Ianus</hi> bee for euer closed: you shall haue them that were your enemies to molest you, a sure backe to defend you: their bodies shall be your aides, and they must be partners in all your quarels: Two snow-balls put together, make one the greater: Two houses ioyned, make one the larger: two Castle walles made in one, makes one as thicke and strong as both. And doe you
<pb facs="tcp:8048:28"/>not see in the Low countreys how auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the English and the Scottish are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned together? This is a point so plaine, as no man that hath wit or hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, but must acknowledge it feelingly.</p>
            <p>And where it is obiected that the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tishmen are not tyed to the seruice of the King in the warres aboue forty dayes; It is an ignorant mistaking. For the trueth is, That in respect the Kings of Scotland did not so abound in Treasure and money to take vp an Armie vnder pay, as the Kings of England did; Therefore was the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Army wont to bee raysed onely by Proclamation, vpon the penaltie of their breach of alleageance; So as they were all forced to come to the Warre like Snailes who carry their house about with them; Euery Nobleman and Gentleman brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with him their Tents, money, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for their house, victuals of all sorts, and all other necessaries, the King sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying them of nothing: Necessitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon enforcing a warning to be giuen by
<pb facs="tcp:8048:29"/>the Proclamation of the space of their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, without which they could not make their prouision accordingly, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as long as they were within the bounds of Scotland, where it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them to helpe themselues by the spoile or wasting of the Countrey. But neither is there any Law prescribing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely such a certaine number of dayes, nor yet is it without the limits of the Kings power to keepe them together, as many more dayes as hee list, to renew his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations from time to time some rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable number of dayes, before the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the former, they being euer bound to serue and waite vpon him, though it vvere an hundreth yeere if need were.</p>
            <p>Now to conclude, I am glad of this occasion, that I might <hi>Liberare animam meam;</hi> You are nowe to recede: vvhen you meete againe, remember I pray you, the trueth and sincerity of my meaning, which in seeking Vnion, is onely to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the greatnesse of your Empire sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:8048:29"/>here in England, And yet with such caution I wish it, as may stand with the weale of both States. What is now desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hath oft before bene sought when it could not bee obteined: To refuse it now then, were double iniquitie. Strengthen your owne felicitie, LONDON must be the Seate of your King, and Scotland ioyned to this kingdome by a Golden conquest, but cymented with loue, (as I said before) which within will make you strong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Ciuill and intestine Rebellion, as vvithout vve vvill bee compassed and guarded vvith our walles of brasse. Iudge mee charitably, since in this I seeke your equall good, that so both of you might be made fearefull to your Enemies, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in your selues, and auaileable to your friendes. Studie therefore hereafter to make a good Conclusion, auoyd all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes, cut off all vaine questions, that your King may haue his lawfull desire, and be not disgraced in his iust endes. And for your securitie in such reasonable points of
<pb facs="tcp:8048:30"/>restritions, whereunto I am to agree, ye need neuer doubt of my inclination: For I will not say any thing which I will not promise, nor promise any thing which I will not sweare; What I sweare I will signe, and what I signe, I shall with GODS grace euer performe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8048:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>